This task is about causality in Petri nets.
And we have been given two Petri nets and
we shall indicate the conditions of all transitions
according to the definition of causality.
And therefore, I just create a little table
where we have all the transitions and so in
the first case, these are for transitions
for Petri net N1.
This is for Petri net N1, and then we have
the causalities on the right-hand side.
Left are the transitions and right are the
causalities.
I do not have enough space for the heading
now because I draw it up here, but so left
is the transitions and on the right side,
there shall be the causalities.
And when we start with the first transition,
then we can check here, can we fire t1?
We require token in s1 and we require token
in s2 and therefore we do not require to fire
any other transition, so we can fire t1 right
away.
That's why we can have just the empty set
here for t1.
For t2, we require one token in s1, which
we have, that's why t2 has also no causalities
on empty set for the-.
And t3 requires two tokens in s2, but there
is only one token, and the only way of getting
a token into s2 is by firing t2.
And we can fire t2 because there is a token
in t2.
That means, at any point in time, we have
to fire t2 before we can fire t3, but we do
not have to fire anything else so we have
just this set of t2, which is the precondition,
the necessary condition, which we add here
for t3.
And then to find out the necessary conditions
for t4, we look at what t4 requires.
t4 requires a token in s3, which there is.
Again, the necessary condition for t4 would
be
the empty set.
And now we are done with the first net and
we can do the same thing with the second net.
And now I write the headings down as well
as we have transitions on the left-hand side
and on the right-hand side
we write the necessary conditions.
And in this case, we have five transitions.
We have t1, t2, t3, t4 and t5.
These are all within our table.
And we check as we did with the first net.
We checked for t1.
Can we fire t1 right away?
Yes, we can because there's a token in s1
and we required one token in s1 in order to
fire t1.
Our necessary condition is the empty set.
And for the second transition can we fire
t2 right away?
Yes, we can because we require one token in
s2 and we have got one.
In this case as well, we've got the empty
set as the necessary condition.
Then we have t3, which requires a token in
s3, which we don't have, so in order to fire
s3, we require a token in s3.
And the only way of getting a token into s3
would be by firing t1.
And we can fire t1.
So t1 is already part of our necessary condition.
And we can fire t1 right away because there's
a token in s1 and that's the only thing required
for s1.
Now we can check t4.
t4 requires two tokens in s4.
There is no token in s4 and therefore we have
to check how we get two tokens into s4 and
there are two options.
We can fire t2 or we can fire t3.
As a matter of fact, it doesn't matter which
one we fire.
But we
require two tokens.
And the only way of getting two tokens is
by firing t1 as well.
Because when we fire t2, we only get one token
and there's no token in t3.
That means we have to fire t1 in order to
get two tokens into s4.
And when we fire t1, we get two tokens in
s2.
In this case, we then can fire t2, which will
give us two tokens in s4.
And it is required to fire t2 at least once,
because when we fire t1, we also have one
token in t3, but it is not enough to satisfy
this two here, so we could either fire t1,
t2, and t3, or t1 and t2 in order to fire
t4 afterwards.
And this means that our necessary condition
is having t1 and t2 in the sequence of transitions
to fire before we can fire t4, because as
I said, t3 can be fired, but it is not necessarily
required because we can also fire t1 and t2
two times.
We could also start with t2, of course so
there would be three sequences and all have
t1 and t2 in them.
And the last transition that we have to check
is t5 and t5 can be fired right away because
there's a token in s1.
And in order to fire t5, we require one token
in s1.
Once more the empty set for t5 here.
And, once again, just to confirm, the table
on the left-hand side should also contain
the transitions and necessary conditions.
Of course, these are the transitions here,
and these are the necessary conditions and
we've answered this part for both Petri nets
and are done with our task.